係。
嗯。
點啊！
哈哈。
噉啊！
我哋有足夠嘅成員去開會啦。
請誒委員確認通過該份會議嘅紀要。
政府當局建議會議改期喺二月廿一日，其實改唔改期，可能到時都。
將會出席事前嘅會議，向委員彙報西九文化區計劃嘅最新財務狀況。
嘅上午十點九至到下午十二點九舉行，咁唔緊要啦，我哋改咗先啦。
二月二十日星期一，大家留意呢一個係改咗少少嘅之前。咁由於政務司長咧就會。
嗰個政務司司長係萬一嚇真係啊辭咗職咧，邊個會代佢嚟咧？我答唔到咧，邊個邊個代佢？而你所知，你唔知嘅啊，我唔知嘅喎。
咁咧就第一項議程咧就通過會議嘅紀要嘅事務委員會喺誒二零一六年十一月廿三日咧嘅會議紀要咧已經發送畀各個委員啦。截至目前為止咧，秘書處並冇收到任何委員提出修訂建議。
咁跟住落去咧，我哋就去到討論事項嘅秘書處都準備咗咧，係討論事項嘅一覽表，供委員嘅備悉。呢份文件係綜合咗政府當局提出啦，以及上一次委員喺會議上面提出嘅討論事項嘅。咁聯合小組委員會咧，下次會議日期咧係定於二零一七年二。
似。
好。
亦都有一啲可喜嘅進展嘅。
即係同時咧，係邀請政府部門進入會議室嘅。
嘅中型劇場同埋一個二百五十位嘅黑盒劇場咧，都嘅設計工作咧，而家亦都係展開嘅。預計咧喺二零二二年咧係會落誒開幕嘅。
噉啊！如果冇問題嘅話咧，我哋落去下一項咧就係西九文化區發展嘅進度彙報啦。噉我而家就請啊，即係。
噉啊！我哋而家咧係歡迎政府嘅啊當局啦，同埋西九文化區嘅代表啦出席會議嘅。噉我就先請政府部門咧，誒或者當局啦。
其餘嘅土地咧，暫時咧係畀廣深港高速鐵路香港段，即係高鐵咧嘅計劃，係作為用佢哋起作西九龍嘅總站嘅建築工地，同埋佢哋嘅臨時施工嘅範圍嘅。
嗱噉啊，唔緊要啦，到時即係都會有即係適當嘅官員過嚟㗎啦。噉我哋下一次咧會討論兩樣好，大家都好關心嘅嘢嘅。第一個咧就係西九文化區計劃嘅最新財務狀況，以及呢個M加同埋博物館事嘅最新進展。噉啊，本來我哋都想即係今次就傾財務，不過即係安排唔。
誒介紹你哋嘅文件啦，好嘛？好啊，係多謝主席，多謝各位委員，好高興啦！今日聯同西九管理局嘅誒團隊咧一齊出席我哋嘅誒監察西九文化區計劃推行情況聯合小組委員會嘅第一次會議。今次係因為第一次會議咧，或者我喺度都誒為西九文化區嘅發展進
度咧做一個簡單嘅介紹先。誒，西港文化區咧係香港最大型同埋最重要嘅文化藝術基建嘅設施，亦都係一個咧為香港市民而設嘅國際級綜合文化嘅藝術區。西港文化區嘅遠景咧係配合香港文化藝術長遠發展嘅需要，提供達到國際水平嘅同埋多。
多元化嘅場地同埋高質素嘅節目，促進文化同埋創意產業嘅有機發展，以及咧係吸引同埋培育人才嘅樞紐嘅西九文化區管理局咧喺零八年成立以嚟咧喺促進文化區嘅規劃工程項目推展同埋文化軟件方面咧都作出咗咧係好大嘅努力。
The lyric.
展嘅進度嘅。
my。
Thank you, Mr. Chan. Thank you, Ms. Soe.
然後，The M Plus， The Main Park。
looking at this end, obviously starting with the CITU centre, and I'll talk about the individual buildings as we come on.
Indeed, even up to this point, a lot of the basement work has already been undertaken by the MTRC on on our behalf.
critical issues that need to be borne in mind is that the work in this area is already well underway, and I'll come back to that. The work in this area is very much well underway.
and of course the central section here, which when we get back from the MTRC, hopefully by the end of 2018, we will be ready to start work as soon as we get it back.
What I hope to show this morning is that this is exactly what we're doing. We're approaching this on a 360-degree basis, looking at the buildings, of course, first. And as you can see from this slide, the progress is actually quite substantial.
咁透過一係列精彩嘅開幕前節目咧，管理局係希望咧增加公眾對西九文化區誒唔單止佢嘅節目，亦都係佢嘅地點嘅認識同埋期待，建立觀眾羣同埋培育藝術人才呢一啲咧，對西九計劃嘅成功咧係非常之重要嘅。
管理局咧喺零九至到一一年咧，係呢幾年間咧係進行咗一個三個階段嘅公眾參與活動，嚟到擬備西九嘅發展圖則，即係我哋叫嘅development plan。呢個圖則咧嘅草圖咧係根據Foster and Partners城中城市中的公園嘅概念圖則咧嚟到係擬備嘅，喺二零一。
一二年嘅三月咧，我哋按照城規城市規劃條例咧係刊憲，並且喺一三年咧係獲得咧行政會議咧係核准。喺過去嘅三年多嘅時間咧，西九管理局咧係全力噉樣推展咧多項文化藝術嘅設施嘅設計同埋係建造嘅管理局咧已經係盡用咗西九文。
文化區現時可以提供畀佢哋使用嘅土地嚟到係發展，即係咧係文化區區近廣東道嗰邊最東面嘅戲曲中心，同埋咧係西面嘅嗰片嘅土地，而家係作一個嘅誒苗圃公園，同埋興建緊我哋嘅誒呢一個嘅誒M家博物館，同埋咧係一啲嘅誒設施嘅。
西港文化區嘅第一批嘅文化藝術設施咧，而家係正陸續係完成。臨時苗圃公園咧喺舊年七月咧已經係率先啟用，首項永久嘅設施M加展亭咧，亦都喺今年年中咧係竣工。而家係做緊一啲嘅展覽。未來未來嘅三年咧，我哋會有戲曲中心啦、藝術公園啦。
自由空間，誒自由空間裏邊有一個嘅黑盒嘅劇場，同埋一個可以容納一萬人嘅户外表演場地，以及係M家博物館大樓咧，都會係落成啟用嘅。而第二批文化設施當中嘅演藝綜合劇場咧，誒裏邊有一個嘅一千四百五十位嘅呢一個嘅表演場地啦，一個六百位。
隨住第一批嘅文化藝術設施咧進入落成嘅倒數階段咧，管理局咧亦都係加緊咧發展文化軟件嘅。例如喺苗圃公園咧，我哋咧係好多個星期嘅六日咧都有舉辦自由約嚇即係free space happening嘅係列，安排各式各樣嘅户外音樂同埋藝術活動，以及係寵物派對。
對啊，創意市集等等嘅節目，呢啲節目咧都係深受市民歡迎嘅。上季嘅自由約係列咧，係吸引咗超過五萬多名嘅市民咧係參加。今季嘅自由約咧，由九月到而家咧已經係有超過四萬名市民咧係參加。M M家展亭咧，由開幕至今咧亦都舉辦咗兩個嘅展覽。
整體嚟講咧，西九管理局喺二零零八年成立八年以嚟咧，其實前半部分咧都係用作呢一個公眾諮詢，以集思廣益嘅方式咧嚟到係擬定西九嘅發展圖則。喺一三年發展圖則獲得批准之後嘅幾年間咧，西九管理局係迅速噉樣開展咗文化誒嘅軟硬件嘅發展。
工作今年喺亦都會有陸續有設施係落成西九文化區投入營運，將對香港帶嚟文化、社會同埋經濟各方面嘅效益，亦都為年輕人創造多元嘅機遇。而家咧，我就邀請西九管理局總裁咧柏志高先生咧，會用投影片咧向各位介紹一下西九文化區發。
At a much more
work has already started on this facility.
是， as you can see， also very well underway.
我們係 at the point where， essentially。
as you can see from this shot, this area here.
茶house劇場，which will give us the opportunity really to demonstrate.
what we need to do next is complete the central basement section, and that will allow us to do the rest of the developments.
The landscaping, the hard surfaces are all complete, completely underway. We will shortly be starting.
exhibitions, it will be open 24/7. There are no doors to this space. It is a public space. Above that, on the next floor up, this area shown in red here, we'll have a small 200-seat
因為一些地點限制，特別是MTR線穿過，我們不得不抬高劇院，以避免噪音和振動問題。這將是我們運營該設施時面臨的挑戰。
The next one at the other end, the art park. Now, personally, I think this is one of the most important facilities because it's the one where nobody has to pay to get in. You can just come and lie on the grass, bring your dog, bring your cat, bring a bottle of wine and enjoy the space.
我的 task today is basically to bring you through the project and explain exactly what is happening on the ground. I want to emphasise two points. First, this project isn't just about building buildings. It's about building the content of the buildings, building the audience, building the programming, and
在 terms of timing，essentially within the next three years to four years， all of the buildings that are shown in the darker colours here， will be opened. Indeed， the pavilion is already opened， the M+ is under construction and will be opened 2019， Sea Chu Centre open in 2018。
And the park 2017-2018 with the free space, the small black box theatre opening in 2019. So let's look at the individual facilities. Of course, starting with the Sechu Centre, designed by the late Canadian architect Bing Tom with Ronald Loon Partners. This is going to be a
Spectacular space designed particularly for Chinese opera, Cantonese opera. Comprises a number of key spaces. I'm just showing three of them here. At the the ground level, we have the atrium, which will be an active space. We can do performances, but we can also do marketplaces. We can do
cozy level that's a good word cozy level exactly how people can appreciate this wonderful wonderful art form and then of course above that the magnificent 1,100 seat main theatre I say above that and this is one of the issues that we're going to have to deal
Of course.
adjacent to it will be.
和，它會帶你從博物館，down到水front。
within the park, I touched on the free space. This is a 450-seat black box theatre.
Chinese New Year and having that view, fantastic! That is going to be the most popular place in town. I can guarantee that.
everybody will want to have because it is the most fantastic sight, and can you imagine watching the fireworks?
represents the the foundations for the black box theatre which we're calling Free Space.
already completed is this facility here, which is the M+ pavilion, and the permanent secretary touched on that, and I'll come back to that in a minute.
Facade which is reflective means that this building will essentially disappear into the park. It's a lovely design by a Hong Kong architects, young Hong Kong architects, and we're very proud of what they've done.
at the other end, this site here is our temporary nursery park, which is already operational, has been for over a year now, and is where we held our very very popular free space happening events.
我 mention the pavilion, as you can see, this is already up, running, operational. It's a lovely little building. I call it a jewel box, and it'll be fantastic when we, when the park is surrounding it, the trees grow up. This
At ten zero seat open space where we can do concerts and and large scale events serviced by the free space building, and then indoors there's a small, essentially a cafe type.
and as you come from the museum, you'll see heavy planting, a wide range of Hong Kong species that have been currently placed in the nursery part to test them to make sure that they're suitable for this site.
The important thing to bear in mind is that this site, which represents essentially the park, will also include this area here, which is adjacent to the M+ museum site. Will be an underground car park with park over the top.
Nevertheless，work is very， very much well underway，and as you can see from these shots，not only has all of the essential structure been completed，we're now working on the facade to enclose the building，while at the same time this area here essentially represents the atrium，and
facility where we can do more intimate events, jazz or poetry reading. These projects which don't really have a space, and we will give that space within the park. I just want to give you a walk through, just to give you a little feel of what we are planning for this wonderful.
As you can see on the right is the M Plus Pavilion, and as we walk further down into the park, you come eventually to this fantastic location right on the waterfront. And I'm giving you the evening view because honestly, this is the ten billion dollar view. This is the view that every
represent.
purpose-built。
and as you can see from the site.
M plus， our major museum。
The design has had to accommodate that, and in this case, they celebrate it.
Of course, adjacent to it, let me clear that is the.
sizes to suit the wonderful collection that we're already building up.
這係一個 fantastic 建築，設計由赫茲奧跟德穆朗，with Terry Farrells and Ove Arup 作為 partners in Hong Kong。
adjacent to the M Plus will be the Lyric Theatre complex, and I can say this is probably the first time we've showed this image of the Lyric Theatre.
我 can say that foundation works are already underway for this important building for us, but within, as the permanent secretary said, we'll have three.
gallery spaces coming off what would have been essentially the representation of the roof of the MTR. above that the entrance level, these trusses.
和儲存，和 adjacent to that will be an RDE building with space for arts and other groups. That as a complex is is currently under construction.
Actually, and people don't really realise this. This is the main museum. The main museum space is here. This is the office and restaurant dining facilities. Behind it is the conservation building.
inside the building, of course, we have again to deal with this issue. This site that we have, while it looks wonderful and is a fantastic site, is already riddled with many different underground facilities. And here you can see essentially the MTR, the Airport Express, going right the way through the building. Again.
The solution to how do we avoid crushing the railway? Well, you put a bridge over it, and they form the structure that is now being put in place to support the building. And of course, above that, various gallery spaces. This is just one. There will be numerous different gallery spaces with different lighting, different effect, different.
work is very very well underway. If you go down to the site today, you'll see these red trusses being put in place. They are to support that long-term installation of the major trusses that will hold the building up. And within the next two or three months, those trusses will be installed, and then the building will suddenly start to emerge from the ground.
District.
會被 submitted。
It's going to be a very important.
important， of course， we must must connect it。
Outside, of course, we will have the artist square.
我理解政府會coming to seek funding for this in in the new year.
劇院，一，the main theatre here, 1,450 seats, designed for dance.
deal with the situation we have on the ground. They are not all at ground level. They're stacked. We have to deal with those issues, and that's some of the operational challenges that we're looking at.
all weather access that we must get installed in time for the opening of the major facilities around that artist square, including the museum and of course the lyric theatre itself.
鄰近區嘅 pilot 版本，由香港綠建築委員會管理。呢個係一個重要嘅聲明。對我哋嚟講，我哋係致力於將呢個項目做得越綠越好，考慮到項目嘅複雜性同埋所建設嘅設施嘅性質。
to make sure that our access is as convenient as it possibly can, and plans are well advanced. The design is completed for the Artist Square Bridge. This will link us directly in to the Elements. This is the Elements across here. This is Artist. Sorry, this is Artist Square here. This is the Elements here.
medium theatre and the studio theatre much more flexible but also able to take in theatre there will be warm up spaces there will be a dance centre this will become what we believe will be a major hub for dance in the territory and of course within the district and the theatres themselves going to be wonderful spaces very.
very immersive, very engaging with the audience with the stage, using the opportunity to make sure that we provide seating for the disabled, we provide access for the disabled, we provide those resources that are important for everybody to enjoy the art form. But of course, the reality is again, we have to.
this is going to be one of the main entrance points to the district. It will provide the opportunity for red carpet events. It will provide us with a setting which will set off the buildings and give us really a what I think will become a very community focused but active art space within the
The other issue that is important, of course, we need to link the CITU centre into the Austin Road, Austin Station, and here the design is for an underpass. It's not suitable to put a bridge in, but we can put an underpass in. Work is at an advanced stage for this, and again, funding application.
Now I just want to end before I go on to some of the programming side, just to let you know one of the things that we value and put priority on, of course, is the green credentials for this site. And I have to say the team has done really, really well to secure the highest certificate level of platinum from the Beam, Beam Plus.
Of course.
Of course， we're also programming。
must start with CITU, of course.
Areas are being tackled even before we have one facility open and running.
我們係 building 建ings，但係 more importantly，我們係 building the content and the future audience。
和給人民國際上，的機會去理解我們在日常生活中所見到的。
We're working with local organisations. In this case, the City University School of Creative Media.
但我也需要brief you on the cultural aspects。如果我 stop there and said right， that's all we're doing。Honestly， I'd be misleading you。
Also beyond that, the other art forms are getting attention. The Producers Network series of meetings and forums, both public meetings as well as private professional level meetings behind closed doors.
The last last time, looking at how we can get younger people in, we're running matinee sessions. We're doing unorthodox productions. We're not necessarily following the traditional productions. We're trying to be creative and original in how we programme this.
作為訓練機會和其他 programmes，我們會繼續與領先的粵劇公司在台灣和其他地方合作，確保演員有機會接受最好的訓練和機會。
This is not something that we can do alone. We need to work with partners, and we've done some very good work so far with the Shanghai Centre of Chinese Operas. Indeed, we recently signed an agreement with them, which will allow us jointly to develop programmes.
We don't have a venue yet, but we're using the venues that exist. The Kowshan Theatre, for example. We are now coming up in February for the third iteration of the Rising Stars of Cantonese Opera. This has proved to be very successful. It's been something that we've targeted, for example.
給ing opportunities for people to come together, not just from Hong Kong, but also from the region, from China and Southeast Asia, working together to develop new programmes, new opportunities, creative ideas in different areas: multimedia, dance, theatre, all of these different.
We're collaborating with Hong Kong Ballet, with the School of Creativity at the ICC. We're also working with the Arts Development Council. We're giving opportunities for local performers, local artists, local producers, not just to meet people in Hong Kong, but to go abroad.
to have a placement two three weeks three two or three months learn and then bring back and share that experience as they come back this is the way that we're going to be able to really take that cultural leadership position and give people in Hong Kong access to the talent that is so evident.
嗯。
千多名訪客，已經今年，我們上。
Heading in that direction, and we've still got three months to go.
get dancing. That's what this is all about. It's about people enjoying themselves.
Of course, the museum, another important area of our work.
是第二個展覽，which is the shifting objects。 as part of that exhibition， it's about design。
on your phone. We're trialling out all these different technologies that will make Hong Kong the centre for arts and culture in this region.
In addition to all of that training and programming opportunities, we're running programs ourselves. This is a very interesting one. Took place on top of our site office.
We're talking about the M Plus Pavilion. The importance of this to us is it gives us the first permanent base within the district to showcase the the collection that we're building up.
60、66 intern's throughout the year on three or six month periods, giving them an opportunity both in the performing arts as well as in the museum sphere to to work with us and understand what we're doing.
Hong Kong design, Asian design, and honestly, if you haven't been, strongly recommended. It's eye-opening what has been done in the last few years in design in this part of the world, and that will go through to the fifth of February.
The first exhibition, Chan Kin Wah, Hong Kong artist that we took with the ADC to Venice for the Biennale last year, brought him back, put on an exhibition, very very good exhibition at the M+ Pavilion, currently underway.
We also are looking to the practical side of things. We want people to work in the district. We want people to understand these are going to be working opportunities for them. The best way now, before we have any of our facilities, let's have an internship program. And within the district now, we're employing something like six.
Couldn't really have a big audience. It's very restrictive for safety reasons. But this gave us an opportunity to reach over twenty-two thousand, nearly twenty-three thousand people through using the technology, the internet, video projections. We also had simultaneous interpreters.
and of course, and I'll come back to this later. We're activating. We're making sure that it's not just about Antigone. It's about everybody having an opportunity to really enjoy the space, even though it's being developed, even though it's under construction. The free space happening last year, as the permanent secretary said, fifty thousand.
come down eighth of January the next free space happening it's going to be a lot of fun strongly recommend and I'll come back to that at the end as part of that we're dealing with dance we're engaging the community you'll see here we have people that are disabled we have youngsters we have professionals we have amateurs we want them to get out get sweaty and
志願者。
之後。
We also look at.
how we can engage.
沿同啲線，The M Plus Summer Camp。
所以，由由，由
group already there who understand the philosophy who are engaged with what we're doing.
One that we've had up until very recently, home movie was very popular.
我們 encourage the future artists and the future creative people in Hong Kong.
稍微年紀大的學生，secondary school， hundreds of students. We've now done two. We'll be doing another one next year. We involve.
changing that perspective of what a museum is all about, but the museum, in terms of the exhibition, that's just part of what we do.
其他 programmes，我講過關於實習喺表演藝術方面，當然，我們有實習，和講師計劃喺博物館方面。
it's it's an important part and it's why we build the collection, but it's also something that we need to make sure that people understand a museum is more than just
another exhibition every couple of months there'll be further exhibitions coming on showcasing different aspects of our collection for that for example the next one will be all about popular culture.
物理存在，和for that we've set up the M Plus Rover， the travelling creative studio。 We're taking the art out to the people。 We're encouraging people， children particularly， to get involved with art。 They're the ones that we've got to grab。 Grab them as soon as they're born。 Get them with a paintbrush in their hand。 Get them thinking about art。 That's how。
instructors, artists and university students to volunteer to help out in this area. And of course, the museum isn't just about art. In one sense, it covers contemporary art, it covers design and architecture, it covers moving images, and we regularly put on screenings at Broadway Cinema Tech and the
狗是 welcome。
That's not me, by the way.
好啦，噉啊，我就請。
apparently we've had lizards, we've had cats, we've had hamsters.
我 saw a porcupine and a parakeet. They're very popular. Bring your animal.
To get that change now, I have two basic questions.
Chinese operas are called Chinese operas, but in Hong Kong.
So, Mr. Chairman, happy to answer any questions you may have. Thank you. Okay, thank you.
可唔可以 lament once again that the fact that on the mainland
If you turn the volume up, it really gets you going. Get up and dance, enjoy yourselves.
文化交流協議，與上海中心，的中國戲劇。
this is a this is about enjoyment. this is about a project for the future of people of Hong Kong, and you can see people are there already enjoying the site.
它 has to become something rather weirdo，西區，in order to be politically correct。但係，我知， of course， it's too late。
所以，Mr. Chairman，我 just 想要 end  with a short video to give you a taste of what we're really trying to do. It only takes about a minute, but it's worth watching. And bear in mind, you could all participate in this on the eight th of January. This is what it's all about.
議員即係提問啦，啊，噉啊，而家就都係即係三位即係撳咗掣啦，咁每人四分鐘。第一位黃敏政議員。好啊，好。啊，First of all, I noted that you've signed.
真係。
none of them carries any runaway costs.
The rest of the works are all on schedule and.
大概係一百億左右嘅，咁但係呢度咧就未計算咧誒二A同二C嗰個地庫嘅費用嘅，咁所以呢個即係整體嘅費用咧，我哋暫時都係未有一個估算。好，唔該，黃碧雲議員。
主席，誒西九文化區咧，即係香港市民等咗好耐，好心急。咁但係其實而家都係繼續要等啦。噉就誒，我哋都多謝誒西九誒管理局安排咗我哋落去誒視察，即係現場睇過嗰個情況嘅。
第一個是，你 mention the fact that the footbridge that's going to be linked to the shopping mall elements would need to have funding would need to make funding applications to LEGCO， right？ Exactly， how many more works or
projects that would need such funding applications, and what's the lump sum you would be talking about, or can you give us a breakdown of all those applications? That's my question number one. And number two, can you assure this council that
And question number three, the high-speed rail works delay. Now, how we all knew it's affected the entire West Kowloon Cultural Project. What's the latest? Do you have anything to report to us? Thanks.
Yeah. What do you want to do with the first one first? Okay.誒，多謝毛孟靜議員嘅提問。一陣間，我請柏志高先生去回答第二部分嘅關於超支與否嘅問題嚇。第一個問題咧，關於嗰個嘅誒一條由接駁呢一個誒the elements，到到西九嘅一條嘅行人。
天橋咧，我哋準備咧喺今年嘅第二季度咧嚟到誒呢一個嘅十琴itch嗰度咧，係諮詢議員嘅意見，然後咧就會係去呢一個公務誒小組嘅委員會同埋咧財委會嗰度申請撥款，因為呢一個橋天橋咧係一個政府需要。幾錢啊？請問，我哋而家咧就做緊一個嘅。
誒，即係預算，噉我哋係做好預算之後咧，我哋相信大概幾錢咧？嚇，大概幾錢？誒，因為未做好嘅預算，所以暫時唔能夠即係畀到一個實數。一，但係我哋咧係會翻嚟呢個委員會咧嚟到去誒諮詢各位嘅。其實喺我哋嗰個工序時間表裏邊咧，已經講咗大概係誒第三次嘅會議咧，我哋會。
翻嚟呢一度向大家係去誒而家交代嘅。咁至於整個嘅誒公由政府出資嘅工程咧，主要係包括兩個部分啦。第一個就頭先我所提到嘅一啲叫做public infrastructure works啦，就係誒公共嘅工程項目。另外一個部分咧，亦都係大家記得咧，就係誒政府亦都承諾咗。
咧係會係全資咧係去誒撥款嘅，就係嚟到立法會申請撥款，就係嗰個地庫即係個綜合嘅地庫。咁誒喺二零一五年七月咧，我哋已經得到財委會咧係撥款咧，係誒大概係三十億到咧係做嗰個地庫嘅前期一啲嘅工程嘅。咁同埋咧亦都係誒跟住咧喺今
Thank you.
係呢個呢一個隊伍，有幾多人？
係會做呢類嘅啊！
軟件亦都唔係話等到起好曬之後先請嗰啲人。
dedicated to education and development, and those teams. I think it's about three or four.
可唔可以增加啲人手做呢方面嘅工作？李書長，你係柏志高先生。我請啊誒總監啊行政總監。
藝術教育、文化教育嘅推廣嘅工作，總共有幾多個誒職員會去做？現在同埋計劃未來，隨住嗰啲硬件會全部都起好。
roots going in, and I agree with you entirely. It's something we must we must continue to do. Indeed, we're doing a lot of publicity around the events, the programmes that we're running there. For example, that there are some
年嘅誒稍後時間咧，我哋都會嚟到呢一度同埋係財委會咧，係申請誒另外一個部分嘅誒嗰個地庫嘅工程嘅費用。咁所以呢個頭先我提嗰條橋同埋呢一個嘅地庫工程咧，我對都會喺今個立法年度咧翻嚟財委會誒呢一度申請撥款嘅。但係你講唔到一個嘅大概又總。
共嘅數目嚇，仲要誒要求立法會撥款幾多嗱？誒，如果議員係誒記憶之誒所及咧，我其實咧曾經咧係交代過一個數目咧，就係誒喺我哋嘅第一個誒，我哋叫松三A、松三B同埋二B呢三個部分嘅地庫咧。
咁都好高興見到有嗰個誒Perfilion有個有一啲展覽開始咗，不過嗰度而家真係埋藏咗喺一個地盤裏邊，即係太少人知道，亦都唔係好方便，即係行到過去。咁所以我諗要諗一啲方法去等多啲人知道嗰度喺。
地盤中間有一個噉樣嘅展覽亭，即係呢度嘅宣傳，我相信要做好啲，或者主動聯絡啲學校啊、團體啊，即係可以大人去啦。噉就同埋即係真係要搞好個交通，因為穿過咁多地盤咧，即係大家個感覺唔好喎，即係真係唔想去。咁又冇辦法。
整一條引路徑係鋪得靚靚地，有有瓦遮頭噉，可以引到啲人，可以方便到行到過去咧。咁咁呢個即係呢個係我嘅嘅建議啦。噉我特別關心咧，就係誒，首先咧就係嗰個嗱，而家硬件咧，我哋而家好多係起緊㗎啦。咁但係硬件未起好之前，即係嗰個。
個軟件可唔可以早啲做做好啲咧？咁頭先我聽到你都介紹咧，有啲係誒落區去個community嗰度做啲誒，即係做啲art education嘅嘢嘅。咁亦都有啲summer camp，咁呢啲都係啲好好嘅idea。我想問，究竟而家西九管理局你哋？
誒，因為而家呢個階段其實更需要多啲軟件啊，因為你硬件未得啊嘛。咁但係呢個唔會阻礙我哋喺個community裏邊去推動啲人關心藝術、關心文化活動、學識欣賞誒嗰啲嘅誒誒藝術作品。
或者係啲設計，誒由小朋友開始到大人都係，因為如果我哋培養唔到嗰啲識得欣賞藝術嘅羣體，你哋起好曬啲嘢都冇人有動力係行入去西九文化區嗰度睇話劇啊、睇展覽啦，咁所以而家咧就更加應該多啲人手去做嗰個嘅。
因為我哋而家就係要追呢幾年嘅時間，去多啲學校，去多啲羣體。噉我覺得你哋而家啲計劃係好嘅，我反而想問就係嚟緊二零一七年、一七一八年，你哋喺嗰個嘅文化藝術教育嘅推廣嗰度有啲乜嘢時間表、具體計劃，可唔可以再做多？
people to get that information.
嚴重問題就誒留翻下，主席唔該，主席。
No, sorry, ten on the M plus side. I think it's three or four. Oh no, six.
Let me try to answer those quickly as I can. Six months too short for an internship. No, an internship by definition is a short-term exposure. It's not long-term training. These are usually people who are either
Direct Theatre嗰個誒演藝綜合劇場咧，本來預計係二零二二零嘅，咁而家係二零二二啦。我唔誒，即係我坦白講，我係想問下，其實會唔會真係同呢一個誒誒，即係嗰個高鐵有關啦？咁同埋咧誒，亦都啊啊啊！
Couple of questions there. Let me deal with them in order. In fact, we already do tours for school groups, district groups, community groups to the M+ Pavilion. In fact, as I was leaving this morning, we had a group going in as a community group, and that's already programmed in. It's it's a regular every day we'll have tours.
Installations in the MTR at the moment. Talking about the the design exhibition, we're also working with schools and tour groups. For example, Suhanya did a training session for teachers to explain to them about.
the exhibitions to bring them to understand, so that when they bring their children, they're already educated. So that outreach programme is already in place. In terms of this issue of software development, absolutely, we have a team in the M Plus. We have a team now that we've just recruited in the performing arts that are.
On their side, so I'm I'm out of date. It's it's changing so rapidly. So ten altogether, they are sixteen. They are all full time, focused on doing art education. That's right. And on top of that, we have the the interns and we have the docents and we have these training programmes for teachers. It would be helpful if.
If you can give us a timetable and a plan, concrete plan in coming years, two years, so that we can we know what programme you are running and in what way we can help to publicise the programme. In fact, a lot of this information is on our website already. Obviously, that's the best source for most.
好，請之後就準備翻畀我哋嘅會啦，因為我哋都想即係即係佢期待住即係噉嘅。噉係咪秘書長都有啲補充啊？主主要係承諾翻畀誒我哋西九所有嘅呢啲活動咧，我哋都發邀請畀呢一個誒聯合小組委員會嘅委員，等佢哋可以參與。好啦，不過我哋頭先啊，聽下我。
碧雲議員所講咧，佢就想要即係預早知道咧，即係來年一啲嘅計劃嘅。咁可能即係係嗰個咧，就西九管理局誒通過咗之後，我哋就可以喺下一次會議嘅時候交代畀各位議員。好噉，副主席，多謝主席。我希望有第二輪，我已經排定隊得唔得？係因因為因為都有好多問題，你知呢個。
呢一個真係等咗好耐啦，噉我亦都好期望。我mark咗diary啦，一月八號我會去嘅嚇。咁咧就希望到時先跳舞啦。呢度唔係好方便。咁咧就誒，首先咧我就想問一問，其實真係好好多嘢問。咁咧就誒頭先講過誒連接性先，我都太多。關於個誒嗰個誒intern。
即係嗰個實習期咧，誒，其實你哋覺得六個月會唔會誒，好似較為短一啲？因為你知其實去訓練一個人去明白你哋做緊嘅嘢，可能會兩三個月先至叫做勉強上手，甚至可能要第四個月。咁誒，希望如果落手落腳可以做到一個節目啊，或者一個誒，即係一個策展啊。
誒。
需視乎私人資金，但係佢就淨係打落音樂劇院嗰度喎。
Once they're cleared, there's no impact at all. So we're bearing in mind that as part of our design.
summer holidays from university or fresh graduates who are still thinking about what they're going to do, we're giving them a taste. We're giving them an opportunity to get engaged. We think.
就話要喺當代表演中心嗰度就話誒，因為已經納入演藝綜合劇場，未來發展需再作研究。噉，我想解釋先，解釋下呢兩樣嘢先。
theatres into that complex, which of course has a consequential effect in terms of the design and the time it takes to do that. In terms of the design, however, I will say that the XRL
等等或者我唔知道咩位置啦嚇，噉佢真係可以投入嘅話咧，好可能誒都需要長啲時間。會唔會覺得六個月唔好合適？因為我都有朋友同我講過咧，即係到訓練得佢埋手嘅時候，到差唔多佢可能上手就已經要走啦。咁呢個係一啲好實在嘅嘢啦。咁到誒我都見到你哋咧，有唔好介意啊，都可能有少誒。
政治上嘅問題，因為你我都見到你有同台灣嗰邊合作嘅，會唔會剷走人哋國立嗰啲兩個字噉樣啊？希望你唔好介意。噉啊，另外咧，我其實咧嗱，坦白講咧，誒，亦都多謝秘書長，我我要講咧，誒，我覺得西九管理局咧，其實落咗好多力落去做嘅嗱，即係我係見得到，因為個場地咧實。
在有啲嘢咧唔係你哋控制得到嘅。噉我見到咧喺誒，我一畀翻上屆嘅文件咧，我見到咧其實有一啲項目係延遲咗嘅。誒，例如係誒嗰個誒Lirek Data又好似延遲咗少少啦。誒，另外就誒有啲咧誒，頭先另外咧就誒係啦，即係個L。
啊啊！柏柏柏生啦，冇得咁柏生啊！大膽講啦，即係佢都提出過咧，就係誒。其實喺嗰個場地嗰度咧，對你哋有相當影響咧，就係嗰個振盪同埋個誒噪音有機會嘅。其實令到你哋好多嘅誒建設咧，喺嗰個設計上面咧都要去迎合佢。噉我就有啲擔心就。
就關於頭先你哋講過嘅戲曲中心啦，跟住將來會誒落成嘅誒Lyric Theatre啦，同埋誒頭先講到嘅M家都可能會有機會咧，係受到呢一個路線走線嘅影響。噉我想問下誒呢一個高鐵對你嘅影響有幾大啊？誒同埋即係財務上面有冇影響你哋咧？咁跟住我仲有一個比較嚴。
實際三到六個月是更正常，但係比比長，for these sort of internship programmes。on top of that， of course， we do have employment opportunities and those would be much longer exposures。we also do training for our staff， particularly the younger staff， to help them in their career development。so all of that is part and parcel。but the internship
是個特別的 programme， 來讓 people 覺得一陣子， 什麼我們在做， 和來看， 是不是適合他們， 他們對我們在做什麼感興趣。 延誤， 一個問題是 Lyric， 是因為原創概念是一個單一劇院。 我們因為各種問題， 而決定結合兩個。
In itself is already a known factor, just as the MTR line, the Airport Express line are known factors, and you design the buildings to accommodate that factor. As we've said, for example, CityU, the theatre is lifted above the noise and vibration. For example, in the the museum, we're.
Celebrating the line, Lyric thankfully only has a very minor issue, and those facilities will be isolated. They'll essentially be on springs, so that the vibrations won't affect the performances. As for the other things, the other theatres that we are still to develop, that's something that will also take into
account the nature of the the installations within the XRL. However, I would say if you remember the the slide showing the the site, it's really just the the eastern most portion of the central section that actually has the railway line underneath. The rest is works area.
係先啊！
係將來西九。
管理局嘅。
幾幅圖，即係一一棟棟嗰積木嗰啲。
嘅其他大劇院、音樂中心、中型劇場就要睇成個融資方案係咪啊？誒，可以咁講嚇。好，阿高議員，即係直頭係嘅嘢。你問下可以。到我啊。係。係第一，我想問咧，我就有興趣係嗰啲灰色嗰啲係咩嚟㗎？
誒辦公室啦，同埋住宅嘅，咁所以灰色咧就係屬於我哋所謂H.O.R.（Hotel, Office and Residential）咁呢啲嘅發展權咧係屬於政府嘅。係屬於政府噉，你哋估計呢啲噉嘅灰色嘅嘢會會唔會起到㗎？即係話已經喺度啊，或者政府從中有得到幾多利益啊？
好，唔該。噉啊，第二輪啦，好嘛？哦，好啊，第二輪。好啊，阿陳志全議員。係噉，主席。噉啊，睇文件同埋今日嘅彙報，都知道西九嘅進度係喺你哋計劃之中啦。噉我自己咧，誒所屬嘅團體九月咧都曾經去誒租用苗圃公園去搞咗一次拼多嘅。
咁亦都嗯都好成功啊！之前嗰兩年咧，我哋就喺天馬公園搞嘅。噉啊，天馬公園就話我哋多人得滯，驚踩親佢啲草咁咧，所以最後咧，我哋就去咗呢個苗圃公園啦。今年咁誒，希望你唔介意我哋多人得滯會踩親你，踩親你啲草啦嚇誒。
咁誒，我想講翻就係今日你畀我哋誒括弧二號文件附件A嗰度，因為好關心就係整個西九嗰個佈局，究竟而家個狀態點樣，尤其是係第三批設施咧。誒，因為之前咧，我哋得到嘅理解就係第三批設施係睇下有冇錢，即係睇。
誒公司合營或者私人融資啊，去去興建，即係而家係未知嘅。但係今日我睇到附件A嗰個圖咧，誒嗱，第三批設施包括大劇院、音樂劇院、音樂中心、誒中型劇場噉樣。噉佢就有一粒紅星㗎。佢粒紅星就話subject to private funding。
噉係咪咁？其他其他嗰大劇院音樂中心中型劇場係咪你哋已經有有錢起嘅咧？定係其實四即係所有藍色嗰啲誒buildings都係存疑，即係未曾知點樣起嘅咧？另外就有個誒井號嘅。
啊，陳以仁嘅提問，誒，正如我哋喺過去嘅小組委員會裏邊咧，都解釋咗啦。而家我哋誒西九嘅撥款二百一十六億咧，係足夠起我哋第一批同埋第二批大部分嘅設施嘅。而事實上，誒嗰個井嘅意思咧，就係話，其中喺當代表演中心裏邊有一個嘅黑盒劇場咧，已經係。
擺咗喺誒頭先啊，柏柏志高先生提到嗰個演藝綜合劇場裏邊嘅啦。因為點解會咁做咧？就因為而家呢一塊地咧，所在呢個所謂當代演變中心嘅所在嘅地咧，係比高鐵仲用緊，咁所以我哋提早咧將佢擺咗喺嗰個演藝嘅綜合劇場，係等早啲可以落成。咁至於第三批設施咧，我哋。
誒，亦都係好努力噉樣樣咧，係喺嗰個財務嘅安排嗰度咧，係誒西九同政府係積極係討論緊嘅。噉我哋都誒呢個嘅討論，如果完成嘅時候咧，我哋都有信心咧，係嗰個資源咧係可以令到我哋咧第三批嘅設施咧係可以起動嘅。咁但係呢一個咧，我哋暫時今天咧係。
係未能夠咧，係向大家去交代誒，如何去解決西九嗰個嘅長遠嘅財務安排。我哋希望咧稍後嘅時間可以咧再同大家喺呢一方面咧係比較詳細啲去交代嘅。咁至於嗰個有粒星嗰個咧，其實呢個音樂劇院咧就係誒喺個設計當中咧，佢係一個好似百老匯噉樣嘅音樂劇院嘅，即係話好似而家喺誒。
誒誒，倫敦啊，或者紐約嘅百老匯嘅嗰啲嘅音樂劇咧，會喺呢一個音樂劇院嗰度做。噉我哋相當時相信咧，呢一個咧嗰個嘅所謂嘅商誒商業嗰個嘅運作咧，係可以有機會成事嘅，唔需要靠西九咧係去出資，所以咧就會用一個私人公司型合作嘅形式咧係去做嘅。咁所以呢個將將
來咧都會係唔係由差九出，只係有一個所謂public-private partnership嘅形式去做，所以有粒星。同樣咧喺呢個展覽中心咧都有一粒紅星嘅，亦都係同樣嘅意思，就係由誒公司型合作嘅模式咧係去進行嘅。噉我可唔可以咁理解，即係藍色呢四棟建築物，你就話音樂劇院係最大機會可以做到。
誒，答答咗先係咪？可唔可以視略術資啊？嚇！誒喺個圖裏邊嘅灰色咧，就係誒，因為大家知道咧，大概喺西九四十公頃嘅土地裏邊咧，大概有誒誒一半少一半到咧，就係做呢一個嘅商業嘅誒，包括係酒店啦、商誒呢一啲嘅誒誒。
誒，主席，係你哋㗎嘛？而家有業權係咪？正如頭先我哋所講咧，喺誒二收嗰個二A、二B、二C區咧，即係話喺嗰個啊，而家個圖裏邊咧，喺嗰個綜演藝綜合劇場嘅右手邊，直至去到一個起居中心嗰一大塊嘅地方咧，而家仲係做緊高鐵嘅誒建築嘅。
地盤嚟嘅噉，所以咧，我哋係冇辦法喺上面起嘢，直至佢畀翻塊地我哋。明白噉。如果係呢個嗰個即係高鐵嘅地盤啦，咁嗰沓地係將來高鐵即係誒港鐵啦，即係我哋港方啊嘛，係港鐵擁有，即係話係政府嘅，仲係誒主席呢一個嘅地。
所以。
國際級嘅表演場地。
對，大家都關心嘅。噉啊，朱海迪議員。
嗱，咁而家而家我哋睇到嘅咧就係。
即係藍色嗰第三批設施啦，即係誒。
由咧嗰啲嘅誒賣地收益咧，係要畀翻政府嘅喺現行嗰個財務安排裏邊。係明白。
其中一個音樂呢個音樂劇場咧，好似Broadway噉，即係有機會成事啦。大劇院音樂中心中型劇場。
係誒，唔該，主席。噉我誒想跟住阿梁國鴻議員個問題嘅，因為我見到誒睇嗰個誒分區計劃大綱圖咧，咁譬如話誒呢個。
如果萬一唔得嘅時候，邊個去畀錢起啊？亦或唔起啊？嗱，因為嗱，即係我覺得咧，呢個係完全不能夠接受，因為呢兩呢個呢個，如果你講咧，呢個係個重心嚟㗎嘛。當我哋講西九嘅時候，話我哋香港冇一啲。
地一成塊四十公頃地都係屬於誒會畀西九管理局去管理嘅，咁所以當高鐵完成之後咧，所有嘅地咧而家見到呢啲地咧都係會畀翻西九管理局去誒經營同埋係發展嘅，即係嗰啲灰色嗰啲誒，包括係酒店啊、誒office office啊、商場嗰啲就係就係。
財誒資產嚟㗎，係咪？誒，主席或者要解釋清楚先係啦。呢度或者解釋清楚喺所有嘅商業嘅用地裏邊咧，只有係零售嘅同埋餐飲嘅設施咧，係屬於西九管理局嘅喺而家呢個情誒安排裏邊。其他咧係其他咧個發展權咧係屬於政府嘅，即係話當西九佢誒發展嘅時候。
咁而家你起咗其他嘢，呢個可能起唔到，咁點搞啊？起翻好起翻樓喎會。主席主席，我哋由此至，咁尾嗰陣時係咪變翻做樓啊？即係變翻做。誒，主席喺個誒發展圖則裏邊咧，呢啲地方一定要係發展做文化藝術設施嘅。咁誒，我哋從來咧都冇講過話我哋。
會放棄第三批嘅設施，我哋仍然係好積極去誒，即係研究點樣樣可以咧有呢一個資金咧嚟到去發展第三期嘅設施。呢一個我哋誒希望將來可以喺翻委員會度交代如何去處理呢方面。你要你要你要明白啊嘛！如果你起唔到嘅時候就嘥咗嘥咗西九啦。
即係你你唔得整全啊嘛，成個嘅文化區即係有一缺冇一缺啦。噉你如果你你而家又起唔到嘅，就嘥咗錢啦。第二就係我我想知道嘅，到底幾時起到先？我今年咧就六十一歲，你哋話要整西九嘅時候咧，我係四十八歲。
我我幾我就睇唔睇到啦？你估嗰度嗰度又係會起起唔會會唔會喺喺骨骨灰庵等我喺嗰度長眠咧？先生，誒我相信咧，我哋誒喺我哋而家討論嗰個嘅長務安排下咧，我哋如果能夠成功係去傾得好呢一個嘅長務安排咧，係加強嘅。
呢個。
貼翻去嗰四嚿藍色嗰度咧，呢個其實我覺得係誒。
誒大劇誒呢個大劇院同埋演藝綜合廣場中間就有嚿灰色嘢嘅。
係係咪我睇錯咗啊？即係佢中間送嚟個O.U.酒店辦公室，酒店辦公室啊，酒酒店辦公室。
唔係嗰個藍色同埋嗰個橙色中間有個灰色嘢㗎，係冇錯。噉啊，佢其實喺嗰個誒松寧嗰度係係點樣啊？即係嗰度有個。
財務安排，我哋可以咧係會有資金去發展第三批。我好希望能夠係係有一個好消息畀到梁議員咁咧，就喺即係一個嘅可見嘅將來咧嚇，可以發展到第三批嘅設施。我希望你唔好同地產商合作咯，因為嗰嗰嗰四嚿藍嘢係一個核心核心業務嚟嘅。如果最後尾，
我哋個男嘢係依賴地產商嘅，即係話我哋佛息嚟提佢嘅啫，令到佢所有佢啲developer有機會係攞咗公堂嚟建設咗啲嘢咧，令到佢嘅產業係更加值錢咯。我最怕一樣嘢。呢個我諗就係嚟緊佢要交代個融資方案咧，即係呢。
即係而家係誒，我係睇翻嗰個Oriental P嗰個松寧咧，就可以對得翻曬嗰啲灰色嗰啲位就蝕落去嘅噉樣。我唔知你係咪揸住一張係大概係喺三十三，即係嗰三十二P卅二，我哋叫做呢一塊地係一個誒商業用地嚟嘅。係啊，係啊。
係噉就誒頭先就提到就係話，因為我我我望落去件事咧，就係誒同我之前嘅理解有啲唔同嘅，特別係即係嗰啲灰色嘅啊，會將會分開去賣地嘅嗰啲收益咧，係唔會攞嚟。
唔應該係噉嘅，正如頭先，正如一開頭市民去理解西九龍文化區誒，就算有誒商業嘅成分喺裏面咧，我哋嘅理解都係話，既然你係一個松寧嘅，係一個而家睇好U C P，係佢係一個松寧嘅話，噉。
對於市民嚟講，佢就係一個嘅發展嚟㗎啦。咁點解可以係誒會出現咗個情況，係畀呢個發展商係向前行咗一大步咧？個意思就係話，而家你可以有一啲完全獨立於西九龍文化區嘅地產項目、商業。
嘅項目咧係做出嚟之後，而嗰個收益係同呢個西九文化區無關嘅。跟住去到嗰幾個藍色咧，就又要誒搞呢個公司型合作，睇下會唔會實ting到先至去決定起唔起。噉我覺得呢個係有係抽咗水，係令到市民係。
係無情白事，係割讓咗一啲灰色嘅地方，而嗰啲灰色嘅地方冇辦法去抌翻落去西九文化區嘅發展裡面。點解會合有呢個噉嘅決定嘅咧？李書長，畀個機會你。好啊，誒，多謝阿朱怡嘅提問啊。誒，其實當初咧，點解會有一個噉嘅諗法，即係話嗰個商業用。
地，包括我哋叫酒店、誒辦公室同埋呢一個嘅住宅，係會個誒賣地嘅收益係會畀翻政府。就因為喺二零零八年嘅時候咧，政府係一次過畀咗二百一十六億西九發誒管理局去發展呢啲文化藝術設施嘅。咁喺零八年嘅時候咧，當然有好多嘅假設啦，即係譬如話誒呢啲嘅誒。
啊，二百一十六億係會足夠起曬咁多嘅設施。我哋嘅餐飲零售嘅誒收入係會足夠支持西九嘅管理局嘅所有嘅文化藝術設施嘅營運。咁但係我哋都明白到咧，零八年到而家咧，即係咁誒差唔多有八年嘅時間，發生咗好多嘅轉變。咁以往我哋都交代過咧，喺嗰個建築成本係增加。
加咗好多喺嗰個餐飲零售咧，因為其實到而家咧係誒一毫子都未有收入，係因為所有呢大部分餐飲零售咧都未起到出嚟，亦都係一個高鐵嘅工地上邊噉，所以有種種嘅原因咧，令到我哋整個嘅財務嘅安排咧係誒同最初個想法係有啲落差，咁所以以致到咧我哋需要咧係同西九咧。
去傾點樣樣可以透過而家喺西九裏邊嘅各樣嘅一啲嘅政，本嚟係政府擁有嘅一啲嘅誒誒地產嘅項目咧，啲商業地產項目係幫翻西九去做佢將來嘅發展。呢個就係我哋想諗嘅一個嘅方向，爭取緊啊！即係爭取緊灰色嗰啲係可以攞嚟貼翻。
好。
私有化，啊！
They are being planned and they will be taken forward. Who pays for them is a different matter. But as far as I'm concerned, they'll be taken forward.
My understanding from our very last meeting is that batch three is basically.
on this entire project, mainly for public facility works, right?
footbridge and stuff， is that correct？ is that all？ one no ten billion dollars extra， that's it。
交代呢方面嘅安排。好啦，噉我哋而家就安排第二輪嘅發問時間。咁時間都係照舊啦，噉就啊，羅曼政議員。
這就是所謂的整合 basement。Okay， all right， for the question for Mr. Pascoe。
Your reply to my the question previously, my understanding is that you would need extra funding of about ten billion dollars.
Up in the air, it's gone, right? And but you you you keep talking about public private partnerships. So are you talking about privatisation essentially of batch three and?
2C，所以包括成本的基層，整合基層，對於這兩個，對於2A和2C，你會需要再回來，是的，是的，for extra funding，extra funding on top of the 10 billion that I've mentioned earlier on。
呢個喺我哋上一個嘅立法年度最尾嗰次嘅會議咧，我哋都有提過嘅。當時政務司司長係嚟呢個委員會係講過，我哋係朝住呢個方向去諗，因為如果唔係咧，我哋冇辦法可以起埋第三批嘅設施。咁呢個係個整體嘅大方向。至於點樣去做咧？誒，我哋會喺誒希望將不久嘅將來向大家去交。
嗰時就，呃，when I mentioned the ten billion figure， I referred to the cost of the integrated basement for zone two A. I know， so is that the amount you are talking about now？ No， because I have not taken into account the cost for building the basement for zone two A and two。
And how enthusiastic sort of response have you been getting from the private concerns? Thanks. Yeah, let me make two points, and it's really to supplement what the permanent secretary was saying. As far as I'm concerned, we're going to build.
all of the batch three, that's my mandate. I don't have any other option. I'm going to get on with it. And so we're already looking at the design requirements for the next. What's next? Out of the batch three, probably the music centre, I suspect. And then we'll look at the other ones. So I absolutely disagree with you. They are not up in the air.
The PPP option, I think, is something that has always been on the table, even even at the earliest stage. But didn't didn't you think that's ethically not quite right? Because Hong Kong people had expected this project to be this and that initially, meaning it's it's
The.
元素，within this project.
冇大家confusion，所有藍色嘅都係由私人去營運同埋興建，紅星有紅星嗰兩個啫。
你係講緊乜嘢？係本地定係海外？哦，我唔會去性格化。我只係喺度做嗰啲對話。好，謝謝。你講咩？
Up to a point, always. So to say it's it's unethical or in some way wrong to involve the commercial elements, sorry, that's just a wrong statement. The reality is there's always been an element of commercial involvement in this. What we're looking at, but more and more commercial. No, again, from the start.
Not for commercial purposes, right from the start. Now you're talking a lot of private investments in it. It's just not right. It's not the initial plan, as Chu Hoi Dick was talking about just now. I have to disagree with you from the start. There's always been commercial.
musical theatre has always been considered to be suitable for public-private partnership. The whole point about this project is it's a mix of different solutions to deliver the concept. The core arts and culture facilities, including the great theatre and the music centre, of course, will be paid for one way or another by the.
West Kowloon Cultural District Authority. However, there are other elements which don't necessarily have to be paid for because they are much more commercial in nature, and it's appropriate in those cases to look at a commercial solution. And I can say to answer the second part of your question, there is a lot of interest because Hong Kong lacks a properly
Functional commercial theatre space. It does not have suitable space for these commercial events. We are approached on a regular basis. I've had meetings in the last three months with two or three different groups, desperate to come into the site, to come into Hong Kong, to run these programmes. So I'm commercial group.
好好好，好討論有少少誤會。其實所謂講緊有commercial involvement嘅咧，只係個展覽中心同埋個音樂劇院有兩粒紅星嗰兩個啫。誒，大劇院、音樂中心、中型劇場一定係會由西九管理局去發展同埋營運嘅呢一點係要即係澄清。
好，副主席。多謝主席。噉我都想誒，既然澄清開，我都想澄清一下咧。請政府咧，因為咧，如果睇翻誒呢一個秘書處嘅文件咧，其實都係立法會文件C.B.括弧二一五六七斜洞誒一五至一六括弧零一咧。呢個咧應該都係當時咧。
誒政府或者西九管理局咧，誒呢個係我哋嘅文件啦，裡面嘅附件一啊，秘書處預備嘅文件。當時咧係因為一五至一六年嘅，大家都見到，因為呢個就係嗰個年份。當時咧最頂頂嗰個位咧就係寫住呢個大型表演場地斜洞展覽中心嘅，但係今日嚟到嘅文件，你哋嘅。
嗱。
冇啊，問號冇啊，你追問啦。
即係第二個，係就係阿阿陳素松議員提到嗰個文學館，咁誒，我哋而家。
我哋就會起一個exhibition centre，咁所以咧，其實呢一樣嘢係係本末倒置。或者大家會唔會都仲有嘢想問？我覺得下一個議程其實可以偷少少時間畀大家呢度即係問個教嘅。好，誒誒，你大家仲有冇問題啊？咦，冇啊。
附件A咧就已經變成咗只有展覽中心。嗱，其實啊柏志高先生，我當日我都誒表達過我嘅憂慮嘅，或者我嘅關注咧，就係關於點解呢個變咗做展覽中心。因為咧，如果我冇理解錯咧，就二零一四年咧，其實你哋已經申請咗放寬呢一個商業樓面面積㗎啦。如果我冇記錯嘅話，咁誒手。
上都有啲比較咁個商業樓面面積嘅公誒，其實咧增加咗超過百分之十嘅嚇。噉我就想問下，其實呢一個展覽中心咧，一係咪呢一個額外嘅商業樓面面積嚇，定係你已經上次一次過已經申請埋包埋咧？咁同埋誒呢一個。
究竟呢個exhibition centre，即係我哋講嘅係文化嘅活動嘅。咁如果係商業嘅活動，佢就應該係屬於商業樓面面積嘅喎。咁當然咧，我而家係揸住呢一個分區計劃大綱圖嗰個誒，即係嗰個叫做説明書，我都想誒誒瞭解一下咧誒嗰個位置咧係需唔需要再向？
城規會申請，因為第二欄即係有啲部分咧，就係第二欄咧，就係呢一個誒展覽或會議廳啊。咁呢個又算唔算係其中一部分？我我想澄清一下，因為呢一個咧，阿主席啊，好緊要嘅。點解咧？因為我我而家揸住就二零零七年啦。阿頭先阿長毛話佢三誒幾多歲話四四四十八啦。
我未夠三十就睇緊呢個嘢，我覺得四十五歲關注組都成立咗啦。我而家嚇即係我都想了解，即係唔係鬥老我都唔想㗎，係啦，即係家陣都仲未有啊。咁所以咧，我就想問下究竟呢一個展覽中心點解突然間會飄咗出嚟嘅咧？而家直情變咗只有展覽中心，我覺得紅星嘅隔離噉我。
我就想了解下嗰個發展狀況，唔該，主席。李司長。誒，或者我先講一講，請阿誒阿總監再講。嗱誒，主席，呢一個咧就當初咧喺嗰個嘅計劃裏邊咧係起一個展覽中心同埋大型表演場地嘅。咁但係咧，西九管理局咧，自從喺舊年開始咧就研究咧呢一個嘅大型表演場地，如果透過一個公司型。
合作咧有冇市場即係興趣嚟到去發展咧？咁喺佢哋做咗種種嘅研究，亦都睇翻而家香港最新嘅誒發展咧。佢哋認為咧喺西九管理局誒喺西九文化區咧，再發展一個大型表演場地咧，係唔係一個咁適合嘅一個嘅計劃？點解咧？主要咧就因為咧誒喺我哋嘅啟德體。
體育園咧，我哋將會發展一個咧係好大型嘅誒體育館，係一個五萬人嘅體育館。明白。咁裏邊，但係我想明白嗰個展覽中心究竟本身係一個商業性質嘅活動？唔係展覽中心點解可以話唔係咧？喺誒，sorry， sorry，唔準。展覽依家係咁講喺個用地方面咧，佢係屬於一個嘅文化嘅設施嚟嘅核心文。
咁得意噉，即係話灣仔會議展覽中心都係一個文化設施嘅場地。咁即係九展又係文化設施嘅場地，即係連亞博都係文化展覽設施嘅場地啊？唔係，我係講喺一個用地上面係屬於一個核心文化設施嘅場地，但係喺嗰個嘅營運咧，正如頭先我哋解釋咧，由始至終咧呢一個嘅展覽中心都係有粒紅星嘅喺。
我哋最初交畀誒委員會嘅文件都係有呢粒紅星，都係話咧要透過一個公私型合作嘅模式咧係去發展嘅。因為如果一個嘅展覽中心咧係要作為誒等同於一個大劇院噉樣去營運咧，其實嗰個咧係誒可能係嗰個開支係我完全明白，但係我唔想偷換概念啊，主席。如果係商業用。
用地就應該正正識識咧去城規會度申請嘅。如果本身呢個唔係作商業用途，亦都咧唔好混淆視聽，因為咧文化設施同埋呢一個商業設施咧本身咧係有個比例嘅。即係如果大家仲記得，因為我都話十五年啦，跟咗係啦，即係咧大家都係經歷咗好多，包括單一招標，我哋撳低咗噉，跟住咧亦都知道咧。
政府好聽民意咧，就撳低咗嗰個誒嗰個即係嗰個誒發展比率啊等等。咁而家突然之間咧就逐啲逐啲加翻上去，咁究竟而家係加到去乜嘢狀況咧？二零一四年我你哋加過啦，咁呢一個究竟屬於邊一個部分咧？如果你認為係文化嘅話，我就覺得除非你話真係搞搞咩？
古董珠寶展啊，古董車展咁嗰啲，係咪就係文化就唔再係係咯？或者我請阿阿柏先生講一講佢而家最新嘅諗法係點樣？關於個展覽中心。Mr Chairman, thank you. I I think the key issue here is is what is being planned for that site consistent with the development plan which has been approved.
我知而家冇啊，就係噉。
我就問未來有乜嘢嘅時間表係去考慮將文學館都納入埋西九嘅啊範圍裡面？
就因為我要坦白講咧，嗰個咩誒星光大道嗰啲首長嘅陰公，真係白雪仙同埋任劍輝咧。
我表示啊，你話冇嘅就冇啦。暫時係冇呢一個嘅時間表嚇，即係未有呢個嘅實質嘅討論。咁噉，你話邊一個位我邊個個位，我哋可以諗咧？即係我哋講緊話。
perhaps look at maybe one or two floors in there for that sort of opportunity. There will be more coming on later, and again we could look at those. But I'll be quite frank with you: at the moment, my focus is on delivering the core arts and culture facilities, because that's what the people of Hong Kong are waiting for, and that's where our emphasis is.
由首席執行官及顧問批准，和當然，它將完全符合發展計劃。至於任何個別發展項目，當然，如果需要進行《條例》16申請，那會進行。但我不能預測在這個階段，即使必要，坦白説。
The decision taken by the board to move in the direction of the exhibition centre and not to have the multi-performance venue was taken a few months back because of the realisation of what's happening elsewhere in the territory. I understand. I totally understand. And it's because of that that we're looking at a different solution for the site.
但係，我可以 assure 你，That we have no intention of going back through the development process, the development plan process. That said, that's what we're working to, and we'll stick with that. 主席，我點解會咁緊張？我講一句啫，因為而家坊間仲有大家想爭取嘅就係文文學館嚇，但係仍然係喺呢度唔見到，但係我。
呢個plan裏面有冇可能咧？譬如嗰個當代表演中心，你話誒佢而家係掉咗落去誒大劇院旁邊嗰個啦。咁未來有冇可能係文學館喺呢度發生咧？好啊，李先生係誒，多謝主席。我哋知道誒，坊間咧係有一啲嘅即係誒要求，係希望喺香港有。
一個文學館，特別係希望喺西九裏邊會有文學館。但係咧，過去嘅討論咧都係誒，即係未能夠有啲咩嘅結論，因為大家對嗰個文學館嗰個理解咧，可能大家都有唔同。咁當然喺西九嘅嗰個發展圖大誒圖則裏邊咧，係冇呢一個嘅設施嘅。咁將來譬如話喺一啲嘅。
嘅誒其他嘅展覽誒其他嘅誒我哋有一種叫做other arts and cultural facilities呢啲嘅地方能唔能夠撥出啲地方去發展文學呢一個嘅範疇咧？呢個可以再係新界管理局同翻有關嘅界別可以去再商討嘅。咁但係喺目前嚟講咧，就並冇一個噉樣嘅設施係喺呢個圖則裏邊嘅。我。
我諗過誒，醖釀咗咁多年啦。其實誒，即係文學館喺而家佢都落户咗，即係作為一個民間團體噉樣喺度爭取咁多年噉樣。其實越嚟越得到誒社會認同啦。其實啊，許曉輝局長、副局長都有去參與佢哋一啲活動噉樣。其實誒個肯定係越嚟越高喎。咁
即係其實佢想問有冇展覽中心？哦，呢個可以拗嘅，將來可以有個位嘅，或者當代表演中心有個位嘅。噉你話畀我聽邊啲位，我哋可以之後再繼續拗落去啊嘛。我諗誒，或者我哋稍後再交代呢一點。我需要同翻管理局嘅，因為土地係屬於管理局嘅，我哋再討論一下，稍後再交代。或者誒，管理。
我覺得我們要對住人問到款，我方明。Mr. Pascal, yeah. One of the interesting things about this development is that we have what's called core arts and culture facilities, which are clearly the blue facilities on the site. We also have other arts and culture facility opportunities within the overall GFA of.
嗯。
同事入嚟嘅咧，係誒我我。
Maybe I can ask Louis to comment on this one.
噉啊，而家亦都即係誒，係咪都會有另一啲嘅？
冇，但係會唔會做得再好少少咧？咁呢個主席就係我兩個問題，唔該。好，Mr.Pascal。
噉我哋落去下一個嘅議程啦，就係關於年輕設計師臨時展停設計嘅比賽。
我哋都係請嘅阿總監去介紹嗰個嘅設計比賽嚇，呢個比較簡單，我哋可以快講。
有相關嘅安排㗎啦，同埋甚至保險都係一個好重要嘅嘅項目。咁希望即係誒可以即係除咗教育展策展之外咧，即係個戲曲中心可以即係做得誒好好好咧，即係尊重翻香港一個好難得嘅本土文化咯。唔該，主席。
available within the site, and we are always looking out for ideas as to how we could use those other spaces. So far, we've had numerous, numerous different suggestions, including, for example, resident companies from theatre, from dance, etc. This is an idea we could certainly look at. It won't be with
在藍色建築，當然不會在CCP側，但有其他側面可以看。我我唔知你哋喺開始時見到我展示M+建築嘅相，你哋會記得有兩個建築喺後面，其中一個係OACF建築。如果有人對呢個感興趣，我們可以。
O.K.啦，噉啊，再一輪啊嘛，副主席。主席，唔好意思啊，噉啊，又問翻啲實際啲嘅硬件問題。誒，第一咧，我知道咧，誒誒話嗰個誒Lyric Theatre嗰度咧，即係演藝綜合劇場咧，就會有訓練場，即係排練場地。我就想問下咧，喺西九咧有幾多嘅排練場地？因為咧，對好多劇。
劇團即係佢唔係突然間爆咗一個劇出嚟啊，或者誒藝團即係要經過訓練，即係或者排練而排練，無論係舞蹈啊、音樂啊、劇啊，都需要極多嘅場地。噉我想就睇下，譬如你哋有咁多大樓咧，會唔會有一啲係排練嘅場地啊？誒等啦，咁啦。而另外咧，我睇翻咧過去咧，其實都有。
委員咧，因為呢個你都知呢個小組第四屆嘅啦。咁咧過去都有委員咧就提話咧喺戲曲中心嗰度咧，可唔可以咧就有一啲嘅地方咧可以即係講介紹翻戲曲啦，即係比較誒長嘅地方，甚至咧係話有即係類似圖書館啊噉樣嘅嘅嘅誒裝，即係有個噉樣嘅誒設設施。
隔離得個字寫住兩個三個三個，佢咪姓名咁跟住完全係冇介紹嘅，即係我覺得係侮辱嚟嘅嚇。即係呢個係我哋香港本地一個咁出名咁受尊重，即係神級嘅兩位人物。一位啲過咗身啦，一位直情係神級嘅咁落得如此下場，即係我係覺得好悲哀嘅，即係。
我哋係連呢啲小即係呢啲噉嘅星光大道算把啦啦，即係會唔會諗過喺戲曲中心，至少喺香即係對香港嘅粵曲粵劇界都有一少少嘅尊重喺嗰度，有擺翻少少嘅裝置，而係唔係好似機場嗰啲咧？你大家都去過機場，得個幾格咁介紹，其實都好過冇嚇。即係你問我都好過。
The two issues here. Let me deal with lyric first. Yes, there are rehearsal spaces, there are warm up spaces. There's even physiotherapy space. The intention is that there will be space for I think it's three different potentially different organisations operating within that space as resident companies. Okay. They're large and
小 rehearsal spaces， so I think it's about nine， yeah nine rehearsal rooms within the Lyric。 so yes， absolutely we want to encourage them to become a base for dance。 on the C two side， two things we're already working now to to do some documentation online so that everybody can access。
access it of the scripts etc for the plays for the performances. So that's already something that we're looking at. Beyond that, we're looking at the spaces because within the C2 Centre there are educational spaces. There's a seminar hall. All of those can be used for for.
extolling the virtues of of this wonderful art form. So yes, that's something we are considering. And obviously, around the CITU Centre and within the atrium area, we could do something there as well. So we're looking at different spaces now as to how that site will be operated. So those are.
嗯。
And just on the edge of where the where the tree areas is in terms of the nursery park.
The actual space itself is nine metres by twenty-seven metres, and you can get some other views here. It's a
Good exposure. If we take it forward, maybe I can ask Kingsley to just take us through this short presentation, and he can explain in more detail exactly what we're thinking about.
Just to give a bit of background, some of you may be familiar with the Serpentine Gallery Pavilion that run every year. It's been running for 15 years, attracts over 300,000 visitors.
Thank you very much. Yes, as Duncan mentioned, this is an idea that's been done successfully elsewhere in the world, and we think it would adapt itself very well to Hong Kong.
There have been also been other good examples. MoMA PS1 in New York has done a pavilion competition. They have now turned this into actually a franchised business that they take around the world. Actually.
enhance the vibrancy and cultural ambience of the West Kowloon Cultural District, particularly around the nursery park. Particularly as we're going through this period of heavy construction, it gives us a way of attracting people to the site, and I think it really bridges this idea between the hardware and the software.
So, just to run through the objectives, and again we've illustrated with some images from elsewhere to give a feel for what we're trying to do: provide a platform for local young talent in the field of architecture and design, showcase their skills, gain valuable invaluable experience.
Values we aspire to have within the district. Obviously, we have to keep it simple and cost-effective in design. The plan is that it can be built easily, dismantled and be relocatable. Ideally, we would relocate to another space in the future.
Flat concrete slab. If you've been to free space happening, you'll see that often it's been covered anyway because we cover it to hold events there. And the idea is that the brief would recognise that this is something that's been used for activities and events and provide some form of shelter.
More recently in Melbourne, been running for two years, the M Pavilion, which has been very very successful, and also the National Gallery of Victoria Architecture Commission. And one thing you'll get a sense of here is how diverse the spaces are that are created by different architectural teams.
主席，嗰個嗰個H M，我哋嗰日去誒行過咧，即係嗰個中庭咧。我哋唯一擔心嘅咧就係我哋明白個設計上邊咧就好開放式誒，廿四日即係廿四小時七日都開放，但係我哋就係驚即係風啊、雨啊噉樣噉，可能令到啲展品受損。但係我哋明白你哋會。
誒，都係主席誒。戲曲中心，我哋而家其實係同業界一路喺度商討緊，用咩方法嚟到做一啲保存嘅工作。噉我哋一方面而家喺度籌備緊一啲誒劇本嘅收集，同埋一個網上嘅資料庫嘅工作。咁另外咧，我哋都會長期做一啲教育嘅活動喺裏邊喺個中庭裏邊咧，我會有展覽嘅地方。
誒展覽空間，好似頭先誒陳淑莊議員所講嘅中庭係一個會好多人出入嘅地方，但係我哋都明白誒喺嗰個管理方面，我哋會小心咁進行噉。希望可以下次大家再睇血庫中心嘅建設嘅時，可以畀大家見到多啲嘅。好，多謝噉啊！即係多謝呢個即係進度嘅介紹啦。
While we're getting set up, Mr. Chairman, maybe I can just very briefly start and explain what we're doing. This is an idea. I'll be honest, we're copying. It's not an original idea. It's something that is done elsewhere, but we feel it's something that Hong Kong young designers and architects will get a really good.
We ourselves have located a spot on within the nursery park. It's actually on the waterfront. It's a really, really attractive position, looking towards the harbour. You get a lovely sunset from there, and it's located near to the food kiosk.
自然通風。
他們可能有香港，或者正在研究。
undergraduate or postgraduate studies, people who are
They will be adjudicated by a jury panel, and we will select three designs to take forward.
and the final winning design will be taken forward to construction for display in the district.
The other designs, we would encourage them to be taken forward elsewhere. We would hope that they can have a future life in another place.
We don't know all about the bureaucracy or all the details. We will guide them through that process. The key is we get their creativity in its purest form.
And require no additional provision of services apart from those available, and obviously it has to meet all the structural and safety criteria, satisfy all the requirements.
The brief itself, again, we keep very, very simple to allow maximum opportunity for creativity. So, ideally, focusing on sustainable materials, green features.
which is in the spirit of the the ideas behind the district, be inclusive and accessible to all, a one level structure with perhaps a higher ceiling or roof, but we keep it to one level.
About what we do in the district, working with some of the international judges, and really, really getting a chance to broaden their experience. So I think it offers a good opportunity, and we would really, really seek to document the whole process in terms of creating positive outputs in terms of video and other materials.
raising the profile of Hong Kong design internationally, creating a new space for the public to engage with WKCD, and creating a model for the park and other space in the district. We hope that this would become a recurring event, and we would do this every year, as is done elsewhere with these type of pavilion competition.
The brief we've kept deliberately simple, creating an iconic and inviting architectural open space for people to enjoy. We imagine there'll be casual activities there, so people can relax, they can sit, we can do talks. But mostly, it should really, really reinforce the the artistic.
In terms of eligibility, some of the companies around the world focus on overseas designers. Some for people who are who are more experienced. We want to keep this very much for Hong Kong residents. We want to keep for people at the beginning of their career because that is the future, I think. So we're looking at people who are currently enrolled in.
Who worked in or in the beginning of their career, i.e., within the first seven years. So these are people very much at the beginning of the career ladder, and encouraging them to actually get. And and a key part of that is how we do it in terms of the mentorship. So essentially, what we will do is we will invite entry.
The mentors who will come from West Kowloon, from the judges and from others, will work with the shortlisted competitors to guide the process of design development. This is an important part because we're really, really looking to encourage their creativity. We don't expect the people doing it to be experts on all the details of the construction.
And there will be a prize for the winning entry and the two commendatory entries. And a key part of this as well is, in terms of the judges, in terms of West Kaloum, we would really, really want to work with the shortlisted entries and give them a chance to have some period of immersion, understanding.
And we will obviously go out. We've already started contacting organisations for support. We had very positive feedback. These obviously include the architectural organisations HKIA. We talk about design organisations, all the the Hong Kong tertiary institutions, and we will obviously contact institutions overseas where.
唔使，O.K.
嘅議員有冇提問啊？
噉啊！而家睇下，我哋誒即係。
ID card holders. That's it. Beyond that.
兩到三週。啊，OK， fine， I'm fine.
關於一個功能性大廈，右，and it has to be functional. You wouldn't allow say exhibitionism.
But if someone comes along with a great idea, we'll we'll have a look at it. We'll let the judges judge it. We're not excluding anybody. The only requirement is, as you say, that they're Hong Kong.
所以我們有非常好的正面回應，我們認為會得到非常廣泛的支持，而且希望這個模式可以讓我們在未來年份複製。
their entry built, that's got to be the best prize. There'll be some cash involved as well. Plus, how much? I'm going to keep that quiet for now. I want that to have impact because I want it to have impact when we announce this. But
誒羅曼正議員誒，just just a couple of basic simple questions. When you say talk about eligibility, you say all Hong Kong residents. I would take it to mean all ID card holders, but you don't have to be a permanent Hong Kong resident, right? That's correct, right? Good.
And question number two, you talked about local design organisations on top of architectural designs. Interior design is one area, of course, but I got the impression that fashion design may not be included because you are talking.
作為一種藝術，sorry， exhibitionism in the form of nudity. We would certainly encourage that within the district. I have no problem with that. It's personal choice. The point here is we want to encourage anybody. We are approaching the professional organisations simply because they're the ones that are registered and who may have interest. But
The creativity and Kingsley emphasised that point. It's creativity that we really want. We'll help them translate it into something buildable. You will welcome fashion design students' entries as well. You see, that's that was my misunderstanding because you talked about also.
Beware of wind loading factors and things. Then I thought it's all very functional, all very physical. Not necessarily fine. My last question is your winning entry. Do you have some grand prize to entice more? Of course, they're going to have.
In addition to a small cash prize and having their entry built, we hope that they'll have the opportunity for a placement two three weeks with some of the leading architects in the world to help them advance their careers. That is the value of the prize. It's this learning experience that we want to give people. And that's also what you
誒，多謝主席。誒。
長長大啦，噉啊，有冇啊石禮謙議員？
Outline in red is the site we're talking about. It's within the nursery park. This is the nursery park site. It is exposed, and that's why we said.
the the I totally support the idea of this design competition, but art design there's no boundary to age.
Of Design Week would be one example, Art Basel would be another example, and those would give the exposure to overseas visitors. But of course, it's it's located here, so yes, of course we'll publicise it. But if you want to see it, you'll have to come to our site. Now that's the the basic requirement.
Mean by immersion opportunities, so immersion opportunities is during the competition, not after. During and subsequent after and subsequently, because this of course after the competition is announced, the winner will be then offered the opportunity for this placement for.
瞭解下咧誒，因為誒，其實我都去參觀過誒西九啦。頭先都講過啦，呢一個地方咧，同即係自由約嗰個地方嚟㗎嗬。咁誒，我想請問下咧誒，嗰個地方同啲工地有幾接近？即係會唔會話誒，或者甚至風力咧？你你明㗎咧，因為嗰度咧其實喺海邊咧，即係如果誒太。
帶緊風又驚，即係又驚冧啦，即係都係安全問題啦。咁同埋附近多唔多工地，會唔會即係令到大家誒喺誒享受嘅時候有啲阻礙咧？噉我想問一啲基本問題先，唔該，主席。好啊，Mr. Chairman，if you look at the diagram up here，the site。
Safety is one of the primary considerations when we develop whichever is the winning design. So the winning design has to be aesthetically pleasing, but also has to be structurally sound. One of the reasons we're only doing it for six months is to avoid the worst of the weather, the typhoon season. And in any case, the best time to use these things is.
The winter, anyway. Absolutely. So that that is for sure. In terms of the site itself, it won't have any effect on free space because we already use this site for various different purposes, and we simply programme around it. So we've already taken that into account. 啊，主席，我另外都想追問下咧，因為咁難得咧，可以即係贏啦。
咁跟住又可以可以即係成個會見到個實物啦。咁又話想即係可以令到呢啲誒後誒年輕嘅設計師可以有更加用用浸淫嘅機會啊！我見到好少，好少見到啲女仔自己文件都出現。我想問下咧誒，會唔會話你代表？
即係會唔會同啲國際誒有呢啲噉樣即係裝置啊，或者有噉樣誒展覽機會嘅一啲地方去進行聯繫？會唔會話可能有個交流啊？或者甚至你可以令到呢一啲嘅誒誒設計師或者藝術家可以有機會可以即係將佢嘅展品擺喺。
誒，其他國家嘅同樣嘅地方嗰度作展出，其實對香港個名又好啦，咁誒對西九個名又好啦，咁亦都可以真正進行交流嘅。唔該，主席。好睇呢個。It's an interesting question. I mean, one of the things that we want to do is to time this, for example, when there are overseas visitors in Hong Kong business.
但作為Kingsley也所uggested，我們想這要成為某樣可以移動和重建某處的東西。在那些情況下，如果有人從海外來到我們這邊，説：「我們想把它放在倫敦或巴黎或什麼地方，因為它是可移動的。如果他們願意付錢，為什麼不？我們會樂意與他們分享。所以我們承認這一點。但説實話。
好。
Thank you.
Let me assure you on the second one, we're not excluding anybody.
但係，有好多 local industry， like。
And we can look at this as a separate option.
啊，何君彥，啊謝偉強議員，O K，何君彥議員。
understand, but looking from what you have just presented.
Any design, anyone come in, that you should welcome them. That is what the whole concept of West Kaluan WKCD is all about.
這係關於香港，和某啲喺香港嘅嘢。外部係額外嘅利益，如果可以。明白主席，因為我都見到咧，因為佢哋做即係誒介紹嘅時候咧，都引用咗好多外國嘅例子。咁如果可以即係互相去交流嘅話咧，即係對香港誒呢一個西九文化區，或者甚至香港嘅誒本地。
設計師咧，誒希望係有一個提升噉。當然呢一個可能係有啲額外嘅工作啦。咁但係我覺得誒可能係一箭雙雕嘅噉，希望都可以考慮下。唔該。係啦，呢個我諗大家都考慮下。即係正如頭先毛議員都講話，會唔會有啲更吸引嘅咁？我呢個呢啲可能就係即係畀佢哋更加吸引嘅，即係額外嘅。
There's no boundary to raise nationality, but going in for young, young, why not for the older one, elderly one? Because design there's no boundary. Why should you discriminate in your entry? That's one aspect. Second aspect is you confined to graduates, undergraduate.
bamboo架棚，has a lot of planters. I think Duncan will remember in the festival of Hong Kong. has a lot of bamboo designs going on. But why not include them? I think you you have confined your entry to such a restrictive level. I might have misunderstood.
It's rather narrow, so I suggest that we having introducing the whole concept of Western Kowloon District as a as a cultural area. You should actually embrace this more inclusive, that irrespective of age, colours.
所以我我suggest that you also take into consideration of the low local local designs. That is a lot of those is actually looking around. You can see that. So you know, talk to some of your colleagues that they can share with you on the different local design aspect and culture.
OK。Fact, absolutely, I agree with you. The reason that we pitched it as young towards young people is that we want to give them a showcase opportunity. Because let's be honest, someone who's older probably is more established in their job, is more able to demonstrate their capability and has.
Had a track record. We're we're trying to give this as a boost, a step up for younger people. That's the only logic. But if honestly, if members felt strongly, it should be open to everyone. We don't feel strongly about that. It will just mean more entries, which is good. On the second point, as as we we have stressed, this is not exclusive to.
or designers or anyone else, we were talking about fashion design there. If we we don't have that restriction, you don't need to listen to my colleague, the honourable colleague. She said, just out of the blue, you just do what you think is. Then we can tell you things that you can do, but you don't really need to pay attention. Just do. I mean, even
Even myself, that I appreciate that you have concern for young, but there's a lot of old and successful designers who haven't got the luck to be successful. So they also need the space to really demonstrate. So I just said we should not be discriminatory. That's all. Sure. I certainly I.
So that that I can assure you, I'll look again at this age issue, the young as as opposed to other people. What I might do is every other year do one open and one just for young designers, so that we can cover both. That may be the best way because I really don't think it's it's something I want to encourage people to have too much competition. I'd rather they were competing among themselves.
噉啊！
要從嚴治懲。
誒唔好意思，我等誒有另一個標誌要開，所以我唔冇聽到，希望唔會重複個問題啦。
要 implement the nursery park， the now the M plus pavilion。
商業嘅用地嚟嘅，就係誒誒酒店啦、辦公室啦、同埋住宅啦，同埋有啲零售嘅設施喺裏邊嘅。呢啲嘅誒，除咗零售之外，係屬於西九咧，住宅誒商嘅，同埋呢一個辦公室同埋係酒店係屬於政府嘅發展區。
Sorry, Chair. I was busy with with some other meetings, failing to attend the meeting in time. Probably I might have missed something. But a quick question for for any one of you. Pardon for my ignorance about the progress of the existing. This is the
The West Kalim Cultural District. My question is, I've just quickly glanced through the paper, and realising that EUR 21.6 billion has been allocated for for this project, and probably it's stage one to
和也自由空間，和所有這些都是已經完成或將要完成的。但我的問題是：，怎麼樣？一些其他複雜的，你知道，劇院，我們有沒有任何時間表為這些預計完成？如果有的話，什麼時候會完成？整個。
Completion of at least of those being coloured, the buildings being coloured, starting from the CGS centre up to the M M plus building. Altogether, I've quickly glanced counted at least eight or nine, eight or nine buildings blocks, theatres, centres.
啊！Greek Theatre， lyric theatre complex， what's the schedule for completing the rest of the project? If so， and how much it would be? Oh， thank you。嚇，呢個就可能係上過以前嘅題目，不過咧就都睇下秘書長會唔會都即係。Pardon me for you know， I might be asking the question which have been covered already。OK，誒，多謝何議員嘅提問。呢
呢個咧其實喺上一個疫情已經答咗好多次，不過唔緊要，我好快噉樣答咧，就係誒二百一十六億元嘅撥款咧，係足夠第一批同埋第二批嘅大部分嘅設施，除咗兩個黑盒劇場係冇擺入去，但係咧第三批嘅設施咧，我哋咧就係未有一個資金咧係可以去誒興建，但係我哋而家同西九管理局咧係相
討論一個嘅誒優化版嘅財務安排。咁呢個財務安排咧，我哋希望咧喺誒即係一個短時間裏邊咧，都可以翻翻嚟呢個立法會度同大家去交代。我哋有信心有咗呢個嘅財務安排咧，係可以令到西九管理局咧有資源咧可以繼續興建其他嘅設施嘅。簡單噉樣答啦嚇。好噉啊！
仲仲有少少follow，冇問題。誒follow少少，仲有餐油。誒總共埋單。如果我哋誒當best guest第三第三部分嘅batch three，我哋未有錢。我哋預計揼埋嗰啲錢落去幾多錢到，同埋幾時會可以做大戲喺嗰度，同埋做。
即係要要運作噉樣，即係。誒，主席誒，主席，第三批設施嘅即係喺個圖裏邊藍色嘅部分咧，我哋暫時未有一個估算嘅，因為其實真係有個估算要到我哋真係設計咗，然後咧先至可以做到一個估算。咁暫時係未進行呢一個工作。咁但係其實第一批同第二批次裏邊嘅主要嘅設施咧，喺紅。
色同埋橙色嘅部分咧，誒嗰個嘅綜合演誒演藝綜合劇場咧，其實已經係將快會落成同埋興建戲曲中心，就係去做呢一個嘅中國戲曲嘅表演嘅。而誒橙色嗰個咧就係會係誒唔同嘅表演藝術咧都可以喺嗰度進行，而又以呢一個舞蹈咧係為呢個主主要嘅一。
嘅誒演藝嘅誒形式，咁紅色咧嗰個誒喺演藝劇場隔離嗰個咧就係一個M plus嘅大樓咧。呢個係視覺藝術嘅博物館嚟嘅。呢啲咧都會喺未來三年咧陸續咧係會落成嘅。嗯，好咁灰色嘅，我仲問埋灰色其他嗰啲就係commercial啦，咪應該係係係咩嚟㗎？主主席誒灰色嘅係我哋所謂係誒一啲嘅。
噉啊！
咁請問大家有冇其他事學？如果冇咧，噉啊，今日嘅會議就到此結束。多謝大家參與。
做好多誒商場啊，各方面啦。如果你哋與民爭利嘅咧，我可以話畀你聽咧，我喺度唔會支持嘅。
費用可以啲地價各方面，而係啲地係畀你哋嘅，啲地有二百一十億，今時今日唔止二百一十億，如果你計埋曬啲誒。
啊！呢個W.K.C.D.嗰個原來個概念，你哋唔喺度做生意，唔喺度揾錢。當你哋去揾錢嘅咧，我好希望咧，你顧及到咧，有好多人投咗地。
What we're asking the designer is, don't worry about that. You design something that's special, something that's going to be unique for this site, that's going to be usable in the context of the criteria, and we'll take it forward with you. Okay, yeah, thanks.
會被參與在那過程，因為我們見到那是一個學習機會，讓他們學習如何將一個設計，可以非常創意、非常美觀，轉化成一個實用的東西，可以建造。所以他們會參與在那過程。多謝。多謝。
contractors come out of our ears at the moment, and indeed that side, the construction side, will be our responsibility because it will be a facility within our district. We have the responsibility to secure the building's approval, fire services approval, etc. So that's our responsibility.
我哋都有宏觀嘅角度去睇嘅嚇，多謝主席。噉啊，簡單啦，好嘛，李主席。誒，多謝實員嘅意見啦。我相信呢個一個意見，我哋會考慮嘅嚇。不過當然我哋全盤嘅計劃暫時都未能夠提上手嚟，提手嚟嘅時候，我哋一定會即係回答議員嘅提問。好。
誒就我我見到誒今日有提供嘅一個資料係講年輕設計師臨時展停設計比賽嚇咁嗰個，我係表示歡迎同埋支持啦嚇，可以畀誒本地嘅年輕創作人士可以有多啲機會。但係誒佢係淨係做設計啊，然之後誒喺贏出設計之後會唔會？
真係有份參與可以落實去興建，以致到係即係誒喺嗰個過程裏邊係誒點樣可以參與啊？嗰個唔知係咪有冇交代？其實都解釋咗，不過我都畀各方答一答你。Very briefly, Mr. Chairman. Yes. Um. Once they win the competition, we'll help them to then implement their design, and they'll
苗圃公園嗰嗰度嘅誒噉樣揾嗰個承建商會係一個乜嘢嘅過程啊？點樣誒嗰個得獎者會唔會有份去誒下即係揀選嗰個承建商啊？定係有其他制度？No，um，the the intention is that we'll use one of our contractors. We have
好噉啊！第一輪就基本上問曬啦。噉啊，謝大軒議員係咪都再想問啊？我我想跟進啊，秘書長頭先講佢關於個優化嘅個計劃咧。啊，我係同意嘅。誒，但係咧，我希望你哋唔好係脱離咗你哋係西九。
係啊，咁咧，你唔好，因為好多時都係，往往咧，依啲噉嘅機構成立嗰陣時個願意要揾錢嗰陣時咧，直個直情咧同個市場去去去，你哋個你同個市場去鬥咧，你哋係冇需冇畀到任何嘅。
啊！利息啊，各方面嘅啦，所以咧，我要話畀你聽咧，我喺度好小心去睇你哋嘅優化計劃。咁咧，如果你有有任何要威優優優化嘅，你係影響到誒喺九龍、九龍西啊、啊九龍東啊嗰喺依方面咧。
多謝各位議員嘅意見啦。咁呢個亦都希望即係啊局方啦同埋政府咧都能夠吸納佢哋嘅意見，特別佢哋關於個頭先嗰啲參賽嗰度咧都畀咗好多即係正面嘅意見啊，同埋即係個後續嗰度咧都有啲建議嘅。噉啊，如果係大家冇意見，又落下一個以前其他事項。